RG 069:157, Aaron Hand Family Letters
Connecticut State Library
Aaron Hand family letters
1797-2011, bulk 1830-1875
Connecticut State Library
Hand family
.5 cubic feet
Letters between various members of the Aaron Hand Family mostly regarding family matters. Writers include Bayard Epenetus Hand, Aaron Hicks Hand and his wife Elizabeth Coit Boswell Hand, Isaac Platt Hand, and Nancy Fanning Boswell, Elizabeth's stepmother. Elizabeth Coit Boswell Hand was originally from Norwich, Conn.
RG069_157
2011-081
Biographical Note
Aaron Hand (1773-1832) of Albany, N.Y. was a lumber merchant. His wife Tamar Platt Hand (1773-1854) was originally from New Milford, Conn. and Kingsbury, N.Y. They had four sons: Bayard Epenetus Hand (1800-1838); Isaac Platt Hand (1803-1849); Lemuel Platt Hand (1809-1850); and Aaron Hicks Hand (1811-1880). Bayard Epenetus Hand moved to Georgia in 1823. He bacame an established lawyer there and served as his father's agent for lumber shipped to Albany. Aaron Hicks Hand was a Presbyterian minister. He married Elizabeth Coit Boswell (1820-1914), the youngest daughter of Captain John Lovett Buswell and Mehitable Coit Buswell of Norwich, Conn. on August 13, 1838. Their eight children were John Bayard Hand (1830-1877); Katherine Margaret Hand (1841-1925); Isaac Platt Hand (1843-1931); George Boswell Hand (1845-1908); Joseph Henry Hand (1847-1905); James Alexander Hand (1851-1923); Annie Kennedy Hand (1852-1889); Elizabeth Coit Hand (1855-1936); and Gertrude Hand (1859-1936).
Scope and Content
Letters between various members of the Aaron Hand Family mostly regarding family matters. Writers include Bayard Epenetus Hand, Aaron Hicks Hand and his wife Elizabeth Coit Boswell Hand, Isaac Platt Hand, and Nancy Fanning Boswell, Elizabeth's stepmother. Elizabeth Coit Boswell Hand was originally from Norwich, Conn.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series to correspond with Mary M. Thacher's printed transcriptions: Aaron Hand Family Letters and Aaron Hand Family Norwich Letters. The letters are in folders as arranged by Mary M. Thacher and the order does not correspond exactly to that of the printed transcriptions.
Index Terms
Alternate Author:
Thacher, Mary M.
Family Names:
Boswell family; Coit family; Hand family; Platt family; Tracy family
Places:
Albany (N.Y.); Bloomsbury (N.J.); Norwich (Conn.); Roswell (Ga.); St. Louis (Mo.); Savannah (Ga.); Springfield (Mass.); Wilkes-Barre (Pa.)
Document Types:
Correspondence; Genealogies
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Alternative Form Available
Transcripts of the letters completed by Mary M. Thacher are included in the collection but have not been verified for accuracy by the State Archives.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Mary M. Thacher on December 13, 2010.
Container List
- Series 1. Aaron Hand Family Letters, 1797-1936, bulk 1830-1875
  - Letters, 1830-1908
    - Aaron Hand, d. 1832, funeral sermon, 1832 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sarah Coit Day and Thomas M. Day letters, 1864, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aaron H. Hand letters to his mother Tamar Platt Hand, 1844-1849 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aaron H. Hand letter to Charles Todd Quintard, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aaron H. Hand letter to his son John B. Hand; John B. Hand military enrollment certificate, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Aaron H. Hand and Elizabeth C. B. Hand letters to children, 1866, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Aaron H. Hand last letters, 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bayard E. Hand of Georgia letters to Lemuel P. Hand and Aaron H. Hand, 1830-1837 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Elizabeth C. B. Hand and Aaron H. Hand letter to Kate M. Hand; Aaron H. Hand letter to Alfred H. Hand; Katherine M. Hand letter to Elizabeth C. B. Hand, 1857, 1867, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - George B. Hand letters to Kate M. Hand; Robert H.T. Leipold letter to George B. Hand, 1862, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jonathan Ingersoll and Sarah Coit Boswell Ingersoll letters, 1848-circa 1865, circa 1894 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Sophia Platt Lines letter to Tamar PLatt Hand, 1844 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dr. W. H. McGill letter to Aaron H. Hand, 1837 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - R. Webster letter to Rev. A. H. Hand (PA), receipt, invoice, 1843, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters from Georgia, 1841-1846 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Appendix
    - Aaron H. Hand stories, circa 1840-1842 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Elizabeth B. Hand estate papers, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Family notes written by Elizabeth Coit Boswell Hand, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - John Hand of Easthampton, L.I. will (1659) transcribed by Aaron H. Hand, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Ohio land from Wheeler Cort, 1797, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      The 1797 deed is a photocopy
- Series 2. Norwich Letters, 1815-1875
  - Lydia Coit and Sybil Coit Lord letter to Mehitable Coit Boswell, 1815 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Aaron H. Hand letter to Bayard E. Hand regarding his marriage in Norwich, 1838 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - John Lovett Boswell, d. 1842, estate papers (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Boswell letters, 1891, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Nancy Fanning Boswell letters, 1866-1875, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Norwich genealogy (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series 3. Printed Material, 2010
  - The Aaron Hand family letters, Volume I, 2011 (Box 1)
    Contents: Letters, 1830-1908; Ohio land papers; Two stories by A.H. Hand. From the collection of Van Tuyl Boughton. Transcribed and annotated by Mary M. Thacher.
    A CD containing electronic files for the different parts of this work has been separated from the collection. Contact State Archives staff for assistance.
  - The Aaron Hand family letters, Volume II, 2011 (Box 1)
    Contents: The Norwich letters, 1815-1875. From the collection of Van Tuyl Boughton. Transcribed and annotated by Mary M. Thatcher; The Buswell/Boswell family of England, Canterbury & Norwich CT. Compiled by Mary M. Thacher; Genealogy Charts: Boswell, Coit, Hand, Platt, Tracy. Compiled by Mary M. Thacher.